<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Ansvver to this quodlibetical question, whether the bishops make a fundamental and essential part of the English Parliament collected out of some memorials in a larger treatise for the information of some, the confirmation of others, and the satisfaction of all.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12062027</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12062027</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 49:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Ansvver to this quodlibetical question, whether the bishops make a fundamental and essential part of the English Parliament collected out of some memorials in a larger treatise for the information of some, the confirmation of others, and the satisfaction of all.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Seile ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER To this <hi>Quodlibetical</hi> QUESTION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the</hi> Biſhops <hi>make a Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and Eſſential part of the Engliſh</hi> PARLIAMENT: COLLECTED Out of ſome Memorials in a larger Treatiſe, for the Information of ſome, the Confirmation of others, and the ſatisfaction of all.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>De Legib. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onga Conſuet.</hi>
               </bibl> Si de interpretatione Legis quaeritur, imprimis inspiciendum eſt, pro jure civitas retro, in hujuſmodi caſibus, uſa fuit: Conſuetudo enim optima <hi>interpretatio</hi> legis eſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed for</hi> A. Seile, <hi>over against St.</hi> Dunſtans <hi>Church in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53271:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53271:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ANSVVER To this</hi> Quodlibetical <hi>QUESTION. viz.</hi> Whether the <hi>Biſhops</hi> be a Fundamental, and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential part of the Engliſh Parliaments?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas a great Queſtion hath been raiſed of late, and but lately neither; <hi>Whether the</hi> Biſhops <hi>make a Fundamental, and Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al part of the Engliſh Parliament?</hi> I hope to put it out of queſtion by two ſorts of Arguments, of which the one ſhall be <hi>de jure,</hi> and the other <hi>de facto</hi> The one derived from that origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal right which is veſted in them, the other from the conſtant exerciſe and continual practice, by which that right hath been enjoyed in all times foregoing.</p>
            <p>And firſt we ſhall begin with the proofs <hi>de jure,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in firſt with that which doth occurre in the Laws of King <hi>Athelſton,</hi> one of the firſt Monarchs of the Engliſh Saxons. Among which there is a Chapter (it is <hi>chap.</hi> 11.) entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>De officio Epiſcopi &amp; quid pertinet ad officium ejus;</hi> that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53271:3"/>is to ſay, Touching the office of a Biſhop, and that which doth of right belong unto it. In which Chapter it is thus declared, <hi>viz. Epiſcopo jure pertinet omnem rectitudinem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movere, Dei ſcilicet &amp; ſeculi &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Spelm. Counſel. p. <hi>402.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; convenit ut per conſilium &amp; teſtimonium ejus omne Legis ſcitum, &amp; Burgi menſura, &amp; omne pondus ſit ſecundum dictionem ejus inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum;</hi> that is to ſay, it belongeth of right unto the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to promote Juſtice in matters which concern both the Church and State, and unto him it appertaineth, that by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and award, all Lawes, and Weights, and Meaſures, be ordained throughout the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly.</hi> Next, we will have recourſe to the old <hi>Record</hi> entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Modus tenendi Parliamentum;</hi> In which it is affirmed, <hi>ad Parliamentum Summoniri &amp; venire debere</hi> Archiepiſcopos, Epiſcopos, <hi>Abbates, Priores, &amp; alios majores</hi> Cleri, <hi>qui te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent per Comitatum aut Baroniam ratione hujuſmodi tenurae;</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Modus tenendi Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</note> That all the <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, Priors,</hi> and other <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church, who hold their Lands either by an <hi>Earls</hi> Fee, or a <hi>Barons</hi> Fee, were to be ſummoned, and come to <hi>Parliament</hi> in regard of their Tenure.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly.</hi> Next, look we on the Chartularies of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, recognized in full Parliament at <hi>Clarendon,</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, where they are called <hi>Avitas conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> which declare it thus, <hi>Archiepiſcopi, Epiſcopi, &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſae Perſonae qui de Rege tenent in capite, habeant poſſeſſiones ſuas de Rege ſic ut Baroniam, &amp;c. Et ſicut caeteri Barones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent intereſſe judicijs Curiae Regis cum Baronibus, quoſque pervenierat ad dimmutionem membrorum vel ad mortem</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Math. Paris in Hen. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The meaning is in brief, that <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and all other Eccleſiaſtical perſons which hold <hi>in Capite</hi> of the King, are to have and hold their Lands in <hi>Barony, and that they ought as Barons</hi> to be preſent in all Judgments with the other <hi>Barons</hi> in the Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> until the very Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death or Mutilation (which was very common in thoſe times) was to be pronounced. And then they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly did uſe to withdraw themſelves, not out of any inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity ſuppoſed to be in them by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> but out of a reſtraint impoſed upon them by the Canons of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53271:3"/>
               <hi>4ly.</hi> In the <hi>Great Charter</hi> made by King <hi>John,</hi> in the laſt of his Reign, we have the form of ſummoning a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and calling thoſe together who have Votes therein, thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed at large. And <hi>Habendum commune concilium Regni de auxilio aſſidendo, &amp;c. Et de ſcutagijs aſſidendis, faciemus ſummoneri Archiepiſcopos, Abbates, Comites, &amp; majores Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones Regni ſigillatim per litter as noſtras: &amp; preteria ſummone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri faciemus in generali per Vice-Comites &amp; Ballivos noſtros om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes alios qui in Capite tenent ad certum diem, ſcil. ad termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 40 <hi>dierum ad minus, &amp; ad certum locum, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Id in Job.</note> In which we have not only a moſt evident proof, that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are of right to be called to <hi>Parliament,</hi> for granting Subſidies and <hi>Eſcuage,</hi> and treating of the great Affairs which concern the Kingdom, but that they are to be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by particular Letters, as well as the <hi>Earls</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> or either of them; A form or copie of which Summons iſſued in the time of the ſaid King <hi>John,</hi> is extant on Record, and put in Print not many years ſince in the Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.<note n="(†)" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 1.20.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly.</hi> We have it thus in the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> the birthright of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject, according as it ſtands tranſlated in the book of Statutes. <hi>Firſt we have granted to God, and by this our preſent Charters have confirmed for us, and our Heirs for ever, That the</hi> Church of England, <hi>ſhall be free, and ſhall enjoy all her whole</hi> Rights and Liberties <hi>inviolable,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Magna Charta cap. <hi>1,</hi>
               </note> But it is a known <hi>Right and Liberty</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that all the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and many of the greater <hi>Clergy</hi> (and peradventure alſo the <hi>Inferiour Clergy</hi> in the ſaid Kings time) had their <hi>Votes</hi> in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and therefore is to be preſerved <hi>inviolable</hi> by the Kings of <hi>England, their Heirs, and Succeſſors for ever.</hi> Which Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as it was confirmed by a ſolemn Curſe denounced on all the Infringers of it, by <hi>Boniface</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Math. Paris in Hen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and ratified in no fewer, then 80. ſucceeding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: So was it Enacted in the raign of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, That <hi>it ſhould be ſent under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>to all the Cathedral Churches of the Kingdome, to be read twice a year</hi> before the people;<note n="(†)" place="margin">28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> That they ſhould be ready four times every year in a full County Court,<note n="(*)" place="margin">28 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53271:4"/>that <hi>all Judgements given againſt it ſhould</hi> be void and null;<note n="(†)" place="margin">28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> the application or which laſt clauſe I refer to thoſe, to whom the rectifying of the Error (which to the contrary thereof hath been committed) doth of right belong.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly.</hi> We have the proteſtation of <hi>John Stratford,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> who being in disfavour with the King, and denied entrance in to the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> Challenged his place, and ſuffrage there, as the <hi>firſt Peer of the Realm,</hi> and One that <hi>ought to have the firſt voice in</hi> Parliament, in right of his See.</p>
            <p>But hear him ſpeak his own words, which are theſe that follow, <hi>Amici</hi> (for he ſpake to thoſe that took witneſſe of it) <hi>Rex me ad hoc Parliamentum ſcripto ſuo vocavit, &amp; ego tanquam</hi> major par Regni <hi>poſt Regem,</hi> &amp; primam vocem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere debens <hi>in Parliamento,</hi> jura Eccleſiae meae Cantuarenſis <hi>vendico,</hi> &amp; <hi>ideo ingreſſum in</hi> Parliamentum pero<note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqui, Britan in Gati. Stratford.</note> which makes it plain enough, that the Arch-Biſhop did not chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a place in Parliament, as the firſt Peer of the Realm, either by way of favour, or of cuſtome only, but as a power and privelege as he ought to have (<hi>habere debens</hi> are the words) in the Right of his See.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7ly.</hi> And laſtly, there is the proteſtation on Record of all the Biſhops in the raign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> at what time <hi>William Courtney</hi> was Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> who being to withdraw themſelves from the houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> at the pronouncing of the ſentence of death on ſome guilty Lords, firſt made their <hi>Procurators</hi> to ſupply their rooms, and then put up their <hi>proteſtations</hi> to preſerve their Rights; the ſum whereof, for as much as doth concern this buſineſſe in their own words thus. De jure, &amp; conſuetudine <hi>Regni</hi> Angliae <hi>ad Archiepiſcopum</hi> Cantuarenſem, <hi>qui pro tempore fuerit, nec non cateros</hi> Suffraganos, <hi>confratres, &amp; compatres, Abbates &amp; Priores, Alioſque Prelatos quoſcunque per</hi> Baroniam <hi>de Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Rege tenentes,</hi> Pertinet, <hi>in Parliamentis Regis quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque,</hi> ut Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Regni predidi perſonaliter intereſſe ibidem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que de</hi> Regni negotiis, <hi>ac aliis tradari conſuetis cum caeteris didi Regni</hi> patibus, <hi>&amp; aliis ibidem</hi> jus intereſſendi <hi>haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus Conſulere, &amp; Tradare, Ordinare, Statuere, &amp; Diffinire,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53271:4"/>ac caetera facere quae Parliamento ibidem iminent facionda.</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">In vita Gu. Courtney.</note> It appertaines ſay they, both by Right and Cuſtome to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> for the time being. As alſo unto all the reſt of his Compeers, as well the Suffragan Biſhops, as to the Abbots, Priors, and other Prelates whatſoever, which hold their Land by <hi>Barony</hi> of our Lord the King, to be perſonally preſent at all Parliaments as <hi>Peers of the Realm,</hi> and three together with the reſt of the Peers, and all other which have Right to be therein preſent to Conſult, Treat of, and Ordain, and finally to determine and eſtabliſh all ſuch things, and matters, as are accuſtomably handled, and ordained in Parliaments. Which ſets the matter as I take it beyond all diſpute, as to the firſt of theſe two heads, or ſorts of Arguments, whereby I was to prove this point, which were thoſe <hi>de jure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us next ſee whether this <hi>Right</hi> of theirs be confirmed, and countenanced by continual practiſe, and that they have not loſt it by <hi>Diſcontinuance;</hi> which is my ſecond kind of Argument, thoſe I mean <hi>de facto.</hi> And in this way of proof, we can goe as high, as the firſt preaching of the Goſpel to the <hi>Engliſh Saxons,</hi> and ſo deſcend unto thoſe laſt times without interruption. By which it will appear, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in this Nation, and the Biſhops Votes in Parliaments, and Common Councils, are of like Antiquity.</p>
            <p>For firſt, no ſooner had King <hi>Ethelbert</hi> received the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but preſently we read, that as well the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as the <hi>Laity,</hi> were ſummoned to the Common Council: which the <hi>Saxons</hi> ſometimes called <hi>Mycell Synoth,</hi> the great Aſſembly, and ſometimes <hi>Wittenegemote,</hi> the Counſell or Aſſembly of the Wiſe men of the Realm. <hi>Anno</hi> 605. <hi>Ethelbertus Rex in fide corroboratus Catholicâ</hi> &amp;c. Cantuariae <hi>convocavit Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune Conſilium tam</hi> Cleri, <hi>quam popuſi;</hi> King<note n="(†)" place="margin">H. Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in Concil. p. <hi>116.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> as my Author hath it, being confirmed in the Faith in the year 605. (which was but nine years after his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) together with <hi>Berha</hi> his Queen, their Son <hi>Thalbald,</hi> the reverend Arch-Biſhop <hi>Augustine,</hi> and all the reſt of the Nobility, did ſolemnize the Feaſt of Chriſts Nativity in the City of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> and did there cauſe to be aſſembled on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53271:5"/>the <hi>9th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> the <hi>Common Council</hi> of his Kingdome; as well the Clergy, as the Lay-Subject, by whoſe Conſent, and Approbation, he cauſed the Monaſtery by him built to be dedicated to the honour of God Almighty, by the hand of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though no queſtion other examples of this kind may be found amongſt the <hi>Saxon Heptarches,</hi> yet being the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Kingdome did in fine prevail, and united all the reſt into one <hi>Monarchy;</hi> We ſhall apply our ſelves unto that more punctually, and with greater care.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And firſt we read of <hi>Egbert,</hi> who firſt united the ſeven Kingdomes of the <hi>Saxons</hi> under the common name of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that he cauſed to be convened at <hi>London</hi> his Biſhops, and the Peers of the higheſt rank, <hi>pro conſilio capiendo adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Danicos Pyratas,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Charta whitlagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mercyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ap. Ingulph.</note> to adviſe upon ſome courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Pirates, who infeſted the Sea-coaſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Another Parliament or Council (call it which you will) called at <hi>Ringbury, Anno</hi> 855. in the time of <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wolph,</hi> the Son of <hi>Egbert, pro negotiis Regni,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Charta Bertult mer. Regis ap. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulf.</note> to treat of the affairs of the Kingdome: the Acts whereof are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and ſubſcribed by the <hi>Biſhops, Abbats,</hi> and other great men of the Realm.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We find that the ſame King <hi>Ethelwolph</hi> in a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Aſſembly of his States at <hi>Wincheſter, Anno</hi> 855. <hi>Cum conſilio Epiſcoporum, &amp; Principum,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Ingulf Croyland hist.</note> by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Councel of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Nobility, confirmed unto the <hi>Clergy</hi> the tenth part of all mens Goods; and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that the Tythe ſo confirmed unto them ſhould be free <hi>ab omnibus Secularibus Servitutibus,</hi> from all ſecular Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and Impoſitions.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The two Charters were iſſued out by <hi>Athelſtone,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned, <hi>Conſilio Wifelmi Archiepiſcopi mei, &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Epiſcoporum meorum,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Ap Eund. p. <hi>402, 403.</hi>
               </note> by the advice of <hi>Wifelme</hi> his Arch-Biſhop, and his other Biſhops.</p>
            <p>And <hi>5ly.</hi> That <hi>Ina</hi> in the year 902. cauſed the great Council of his Realm to be Aſſembled, conſiſting <hi>ex Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis, Principibus, Proceribus,</hi> &amp;c. of Biſhops, Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Earls, and of all the wiſe men, Elders, and people of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53271:5"/>the whole Kingdom, and there Enacted divers Laws for the Weal of his Realm.<note n="(†)" place="margin">ap. cund. p. <hi>219.</hi>
               </note> We alſo read this in the Reign of <hi>Edrid,</hi> Anno 948. <hi>viz. In festo igitur nativitatis</hi> Beatae Mariae <hi>cum univerſi Magnates Regni per Regium edictum ſummoniri, tam</hi> Archiepiſcopi, <hi>&amp;</hi> Epiſcopi, <hi>ac</hi> Abbates, <hi>quam caeteri totius Regni proceres &amp; optimates</hi> Londiniis <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſſent ad tractandum de negotijs publicis totius Regni;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Id ibid. p. <hi>497.</hi> edit. Lon.</note> That in the Feaſt of the Nativity of the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> the great men of the Realm, that is to ſay <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,</hi> Nobles, Peers, were ſummoned by the Kings Writ to appear at <hi>London,</hi> to handle, and conclude about the publick Affairs of the Kingdom. Mention of which Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is made again at the foundation and endowment of the Abby of <hi>Crowland;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">M. id p. <hi>500.</hi>
               </note> and afterwards a confirmation of the ſame by <hi>Edgar,</hi> Anno. 966. <hi>Praeſentibus Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus, &amp; optimatibus Regni;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id p.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 1.50.</note> In the preſence of <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> Abbots, and Peers of the Realm. The like Convention of <hi>Eſtates</hi> we find to have been called by <hi>Canutus</hi> the <hi>Dane,</hi> after the death of <hi>Edmund Ironſide,</hi> for the ſetling the Crown on his own head, of which thus the Author<note n="(†)" place="margin">Rog. Heveden An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. pag. prior p. <hi>250.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cujus poſt mortem Rex</hi> Canu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>omnes</hi> Epiſcopos, <hi>&amp; Duces, nec non &amp; Principes, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoſque optimates gentis</hi> Angliae, Londoniae <hi>congregari juſſit.</hi> Where we ſtill find the <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be called to <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as the Dukes, Princes, and the reſt of the Nobility; and to be ranked and marſhalled firſt, (which clearly ſhews that they were alwayes reckoned for the <hi>firſt Eſtate</hi>) before the greateſt, and moſt eminent of the <hi>ſecular</hi> Peers. And ſo we find it alſo in a Charter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> the laſt King of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Race) by which he granted certain Lands, and Privileges to the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Anno 1066. <hi>Cum Concilio, &amp; deereto</hi> Archiepiſcoporum, Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, <hi>Comitum aliorumque optimatum;</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">ap. H. Spel. in Concil. p. <hi>630.</hi>
               </note> with the Counſel and Decree of the <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> Earls, and others of his Nobles. And all this while the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and other Prelates of the Church did hold by no other Tenure, than <hi>in purô &amp; perpetuô Eleemoſynâ;</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Camden in Brit.</note> 
               <hi>or frank Almoigne,</hi> as our Lawyers call it: and therefore ſate in <hi>Parliament</hi> in no other capacity than as ſpiritual perſons meerly; who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53271:6"/>by their extraordinary knowledge in the Word of God, and in ſuch other parts of Learning, as the world then knew, were thought beſt able to direct and adviſe their Princes in all points of difficulty. But when the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour had poſſeſt the State, then the caſe was altered. The <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> of the Church were no longer ſuffered to hold their Land in <hi>frank Almoigne,</hi> as before they did, or to be free from ſecular ſervices and commands, as before they were. Although they kept their Lands, yet they changed their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, and by the Conquerour were ordained to hold their Lands, <hi>ſub militari ſervitute,</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">Mat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in will. <hi>1.</hi> An. <hi>1070.</hi>
               </note> either in <hi>Capite,</hi> or by <hi>Baronage,</hi> or ſome ſuch <hi>military</hi> hold, and thereby were compellable to aid the Kings in all times of War, with Men, Arms, and Horſes, as the Lay-Subjects of the ſame <hi>Tenures</hi> were required to do.</p>
            <p>Which though it were conceived to be a great <hi>disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſement</hi> at the firſt, and an heavy burthen to the <hi>Prelacy;</hi> yet it conduced at laſt to their greater honour, in giving them a further title to their place in <hi>Parliament,</hi> than that which formerly they could pretend to. Before, they claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a place therein, <hi>ratione Officij,</hi> only by reaſon of their Offices, or <hi>Spiritual</hi> Dignities; But after this, by reaſon alſo of thoſe <hi>Baronies</hi> which were erected, and annexed to their ſeveral Dignities; <hi>En respect de lour poſſeſſions L' anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Baronies annexes a lour dignities</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Stanford Pleas. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as our Lawyers have it. From this time forwards we muſt look upon them in the Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> not as Biſhops only, but as <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the Realm alſo; and ſo themſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to the Tempotal Lords in the <hi>Parliament</hi> holden at <hi>Northampton,</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Non ſedimus hic</hi> Epiſcopi, <hi>ſed</hi> Barones <hi>Pares hic ſumus;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Selden titles of hon. p. <hi>2.18.</hi>
               </note> We ſit not here ſay they, as <hi>Biſhops only,</hi> but as <hi>Barons;</hi> we are <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons,</hi> and you are <hi>Barons;</hi> here we ſit as <hi>Peers.</hi> Which laſt is alſo verified <hi>terminis,</hi> by the words of a Statute, or Act of Parliament, wherein the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are acknowledged to be <hi>Peers of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed more particularly to our proofs <hi>de facto,</hi> after the alteration of their Tenures by the <hi>Norman</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, we find a Parliament aſſembled in the fifth year of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53271:6"/>that King wherein are preſent <hi>Epiſcopi, Abbates, Comites, &amp; primats totius Angliae,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Math. Paris in willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmo <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbats, Earls, and the reſt of the Baronage of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>3ly.</hi> In the ninth year of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> an old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor telleth us, <hi>de regni statu acturus,</hi> Epiſcopos, <hi>Abbates, &amp; quoſcunque regni proceres in unum praecepti ſui ſanctione egit,</hi> that being to conſult of the Affairs of the Kingdom, he called together by his Writ the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbots, and all the Peers of the Realm,<note n="(†)" place="margin">Eadmer hiſt. Nov. l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>3ly.</hi> During the raign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt (for we will take but one example out of each Kings raign, though each Kings raign would yeild us more) a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was called at <hi>London,</hi> wherein were many things diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched, as well of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> as Secular nature, the <hi>Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops,</hi> and Abbots being preſent with the other Lords; <hi>Coact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> apud</hi> Londoniam <hi>Magno</hi> Epiſcoporum, <hi>&amp; Procerum, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batumque conſilio,</hi> multa Eccleſiaſticarum, &amp; Secubarium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ordinata negotia, dieiſa Litigia, ſaith the Monk of <hi>Malmsbury</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. Hist. Reg. Ang. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And of this <hi>Parliament</hi> it is, I take it, that <hi>Edmor</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Hiſt. Novel. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 91.</p>
            <p>Proceed we <hi>4ly.</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond (for King <hi>Stephens</hi> Raign was ſo full of Wars and Tumults, that there is very little to be found of <hi>Parliaments</hi>) and there we find the <hi>Biſhops</hi> with the other <hi>Peers,</hi> convened in Parliament for the determination of the points in controverſie between <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Sancho</hi> King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by compromiſe to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and here determined by King <hi>Henry</hi> amongſt other things, <hi>Habito cum</hi> Epiſcopis, <hi>Comitibus</hi> &amp; <hi>Baronibus</hi> cum deliberatione <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> as in <hi>Roger Hoveden.</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Hoveden Annal. pac. Roſe in H n. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly.</hi> Next time comes <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, his Son; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whoſe Impriſonment by the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> his Brother <hi>John</hi> then Earl of <hi>Moriton,</hi> endeavoured by force and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Normandy</hi> to ſet the Crown on his own head: which cauſed <hi>Hubert</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to call a Parliament (<hi>Convocatis coram eo Epiſcopis, Comitibus &amp; Baronibus Regni,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Id. in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</note> wherein the Biſhops, Earls, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, did with one conſent agree to ſeize on his Eſtate, and ſuppreſſe his power, the better to preſerve the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53271:7"/>in Wealth, Peace, and Safety.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly.</hi> After ſucceeded <hi>John</hi> and he calls a <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein were certain Laws made for the defence of this Kingdome, <hi>Communi aſcenſu</hi> Archiepiſcoporum, Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, <hi>Comitum, Baronum &amp; omnium fidelium ſuorum Angliae,</hi> by the Common Counſel and Aſſent of the <hi>Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> Earls, Barons, and the reſt of his Lieges. (Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what was ſaid before touching the Writ of Summons in the ſaid Kings time) from this time till the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> of King <hi>Charles,</hi> there is no Kings Reign of which we have not many, (though not all) the Acts of Parliament ſtill in Print amongſt us. Nor is there any Act of Parliament in the Printed Books, to the Enacting of which the Biſhops Approbation and Conſent is not plainly ſpecified, either in the general <hi>Proeme</hi> ſet before the Acts, or in the body of the Acts themſelves, as by the Books themſelves doth at large appear.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7ly.</hi> And to this kind of proof may be further added the Form and Manner of the Writ, by which the Prelates in all times have been called to Parliament, being the very Law <hi>Verbatim,</hi> with that which is directed to the Temporal Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, ſave that the Spiritual Lords are commanded to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Service, <hi>in fide &amp; dilectione,</hi> the Temporal <hi>in fide &amp; Homagio,</hi> and of late times <hi>in fide &amp; Ligeantia quibus nobis tenemini.</hi> A Form or Copie of which Summons as antient as King <hi>Johns</hi> time, is ſtill reſerved upon Record, directed <hi>Nominatim</hi> to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Titles of Hon. part <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and then a <hi>ſcriptum eſt ſimiliter</hi> to the reſidue of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbates, Earls, and Barons. Then adde the <hi>Privilege</hi> of Parliament for themſelves and their Servants, during the time of the Seſſions; the Liberty to <hi>kill, and take one or two of the Kings Deer, as they paſſe by any of his Foreſts in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> to Parliament <hi>upon his Commandment,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Charta de foreſta cap.</note> their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of the ſame immunities, which are and have been heretofore injoyed by the <hi>Temporal</hi> Barons;<note n="(†)" place="margin">Camden in Britania.</note> and tell me if the Biſhops did not ſit in <hi>Parliament</hi> by as good a Title as the Temporal Lords, and therefore certainly <hi>Eſſential, Fundamental</hi> parts of the Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>By this diſcourſe it may appear, that the Biſhops Sit and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53271:7"/>Vote in Parliament by a double capacity; as Biſhops firſt in reference to their ſeveral Sees, and ſecondly as <hi>Peers</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their <hi>Baronies.</hi> In both reſpects accounted one of the three Eſtates, and the firſt alſo of the three, as from the Premiſes may be gathered without any great trouble. But in ſo nice a point as this, we ſhall not only build upon gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Inferences,</hi> but particular <hi>Evidences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt it is affirmed by <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> in his relation of the Life and Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>5th. That when his Funerals were ended, the</hi> 3 <hi>Eſtates of the Realm of</hi> England <hi>did aſſemble together, and declare his Son King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 6th. <hi>being an Infant of</hi> 8 <hi>Months old, to be their Soveraign Lord,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Tit. Liv. M. S. in Bibl. Bodl.</note> as his Heir and Succeſſor. And three Eſtates there could not be to perform that ſervice, unleſſe the Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops were acknowledged to be one of the number.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly.</hi> 
               <q>In the Parliament Roles of King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, there is mention of a Bill, or Parchment preſented to that Prince, being then Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and in the name of the 3 <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> that is to wit, of the <hi>Lords Spiritual,</hi> and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and of the Commons by name: which for as much as neither the ſaid 3 <hi>Eſtates,</hi> nor the perſous which deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it on their behalf, were then aſſembled in form of Parliament, was afterwards in the firſt Parliament of that King, by the ſame <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> aſſembled in this preſent Parliament (I ſpeak the very words of the Act it ſelf) and by Authority of the ſame enrolled, recorded, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved;<note n="(†)" place="margin">An. Speed in K. Rich. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> And at the requeſt and by the aſſent of the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> of this Realm, that is to ſay, the Lords <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of this Land Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this preſent Parliament, and by Authority of the ſame it be pronounced, decreed, and declared, that our ſaid Soveraign Lord the King was, and is the very and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Heir of this Realm of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>3ly.</hi> So it is acknowledged in a<note n="(†)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Eliz. Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 3. where the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal, and the Commons in that Parliament Aſſembled,</hi> being ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and <hi>in terminis</hi> to repreſent the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> did recognize the Queens <hi>Majeſtie to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53271:8"/>their true, Lawful and Undoubted Soveraign Leig'd Lady</hi> and <hi>Queen.</hi> And in a <hi>Statute</hi> of the <hi>8th.</hi> year of the ſaid Queens Reign, the Biſhops and Clergy are declared to be the <hi>greateſt Eſtates of the Realm;</hi> and called the <hi>High Eſtate of Prelacy,</hi> in another place.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be thought unneceſſary, or impertinent to adde the Teſtimony and Authority of a private perſon, to that which hath been ſaid by our Laws and Statutes. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſuch a Perſon as was accounted for the Oracle of Law when he ſerved in Parliament his Judgement may be taken for a creditable and ſufficient Evidence in the preſent Caſe. It is the Teſtimony and Authority of Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> ſucceſſively Chief Juſtice of either Bench; who in his book <hi>concerning the Juriſdiction of Courts,</hi> ſpeaks thus of Parliaments,<note n="(†)" place="margin">Coke of Parl. Fol. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>This Court (ſaith he) conſiſteth of the Kings Majeſty ſitting there as in his Royal Politick Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and of the three Eſtates of the Realm, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Lords Spiritual, <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who ſit there by Succeſſion in reſpect of their Counties, Baronies, parcel of their Biſhopricks which they hold alſo in their Politick Capacity; And every one of theſe when any Parliament is to be holden, ought <hi>ex debito Juſtitiae</hi> to have a Writ of Summons. Secondly, the Lords Temporal, Dukes, Marqueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Earls, Viſcounts, and Barons, who ſit there by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their dignities, which they hold by Diſcent or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and likewiſe every one of theſe being of full age, ought to have a Writ of Summons <hi>Ex debito Juſtitiae.</hi> The <hi>3d. Eſtate</hi> is the Commons of the Realm, whereof there be Knights of Shires or Counties, Citizens of Cities, and Burgeſſes of Burghes. All which are reſpectively Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Shires or Counties, Cities and Boroughs, by force of the Kings Writ <hi>ex debito Juſtitiae,</hi> and none of them ought to be omitted: And theſe repreſent all the Commons of the whole Realm, and are truſted for them.</q> So He, and this is plain enough beyond all exception.</p>
            <p>Adde hereunto <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> that in all Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the <hi>Gothick Model,</hi> there are no more nor fewer than three eſtates, convented at the will and pleaſure of the Supreme Prince, for their aſſiſtance and advice in Affairs of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53271:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſequence; that is to ſay, the Biſhops and other Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical perſons who are alwayes one, the <hi>Nobles</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Commons</hi> of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Provinces;</hi> For ſo we find it in the Conſtitution of the Roman Empire and the Realms of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>France, Poland Hungary,</hi> together with thoſe of <hi>Dane mark, Sweden,</hi> and the Realm of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And it were ſtrange if in the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus ordinum,</hi> the Biſhops ſhould have been left out and none at all elected to preſent the <hi>Clergy.</hi> But being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the reſt in thoſe publique meetings, and being look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on as the <hi>firſt Eſtate</hi> in the <hi>Stile</hi> of that <hi>Court;</hi> it muſt needs be, that their excluſion ſhakes the very fundamentals of the ſaid Aſſemblies, and makes the whole <hi>Body</hi> to be maimed and mutilated for want of ſuch a <hi>principal Member,</hi> ſo neceſſary to the making up of the whole <hi>Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But againſt all this it is objected, firſt, that ſome Acts have paſſed in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to which the <hi>Prelates</hi> did not <hi>Vote,</hi> nor could be preſent in the Houſe when the Bill was paſſed; as in the ſentencing to death, or mutilation of a guilty perſon: as doth appear both by the Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions recognized at <hi>Clarendon,</hi> and the following practice. This hath been touched upon before, and we told you then, that this reſtraint was laid upon them, not by the common Law of <hi>England,</hi> or any <hi>Act</hi> or Ordinance of the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> by which they were diſabled to attend that ſervice. It was their own voluntary Act, none compelled them to it, but only out of a conformity to ſome former Canons, <hi>ad Sanctorum Canonum inſtituta,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqui. Britan. in Gul. Courtney.</note> as their own words are) by which it was not lawful for the <hi>Clergy men,</hi> to be either Judges or Aſſeſſors in <hi>cauſa ſanguinis</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Conſtitut. Oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Fol. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note>. And yet they took ſuch care to preſerve their Intereſts that they did not only give their <hi>Proxies</hi> for the repreſenting of their perſons but did put up their proteſtations, with a <hi>ſalvo jure,</hi> for the preſerving of their Rights for the time to come: <hi>Jure</hi> Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis <hi>&amp; intereſſendi in dicto Parliamento</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqu. Britan. in Gul. Courtaey.</note> 
               <hi>quoad omnia &amp; ſingula ibi exercenda in omnibus ſemper ſalvo,</hi> as the manner was. Examples of the which are as full and frequent, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53271:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>their withdrawing themſelves on the ſaid occaſions.</p>
            <p>But then the main Objection is, that as ſome <hi>Acts</hi> have paſſed in <hi>Parliamen, abſentibus Prelatis,</hi> when the Biſhops did abſent themſelves of their own accord; ſo many things have been tranſacted in the Parliament <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> when the Clergy have been excluded or put out of the Houſe by ſome <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Ordinance.</hi> A <hi>Preſident</hi> for this hath been ſound and publiſhed by ſuch as envied that poor remnant of the Churches honour: though poſſibly they will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deceived in their greateſt hopes, and yet the evidence will not ſerve to evince the cauſe. The Author of the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet entituled, <hi>the Prerogative</hi> and <hi>practice of Parliaments,</hi> firſt layes this <hi>Tenet</hi> for his ground, that many good <hi>Acts</hi> of Parliament may be made, though the <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould not conſent unto them<note n="(†)" place="margin">Printed at London, <hi>1628</hi> p. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> (which is a point that no man doubts of, conſidering how eaſily their <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> may be over-ruled by the far greater number of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Peers.</hi>) Then he adds that in a Parliament holden at St. <hi>Edmunsbury,</hi> 1196. in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, a Statute was made by the King, the Barons, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>excluſo Clero,</hi> and for the proof hereof referres us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Biſhop <hi>Jewill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Biſhop <hi>Jewill</hi> ſaith indeed, <q>That in a Parliament holden at St. <hi>Edmunsbury</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1296. the Archbiſhops and Biſhops were quite ſhut forth, and yet the Parliament holden, and good and wholeſome Lawes were there Enacted, the departing or abſence of the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> notwithſtanding.<note n="(†)" place="margin">Defence of the Apolog. part <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> S. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> In the Records whereof it is written thus, <hi>Habito Rex cum Baronibus ſuis Parliamento, &amp; Clero excluſo, ſtatutum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> The King keeping the Parliament with his Barons, the Clergie, (that is to ſay, the <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi>) being ſhut forth, it was enacted, &amp;c.</q> Wherein who doth not ſee, if he hath any eyes, that by this reaſon, (if the proof be good) many good <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> may be made, though the <hi>Commons</hi> either out of abſence or oppoſition ſhould not conſent unto the ſame: of whoſe conſent unto that <hi>Statute</hi> (whoſoever it was) there is as little to be found in that <hi>Record,</hi> as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the <hi>Biſhops.</hi> But for anſwer unto ſo much of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53271:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Reeord</hi> ſo often ſpoke of, and applauded, as concerns the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, we ſay, that this (if it be truly ſenced, as I think it is not) was the particular Act of an Angry and offended King againſt his <hi>Clergy,</hi> not to be drawn into example as a proof or argument againſt a moſt clear, known, and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Right.</p>
            <p>The cauſe ſtood thus, A Conſtitution had been made by <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth: <hi>Ne aliqua collecta ex eccleſiaſtic is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventibus Regi, aut cuivis alij Principi concedatur;</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Math. weſtm. in Edw. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Clergie men</hi> ſhould not pay any Tax or Tallage unto Kings or Princes out of their Spiritual preferments, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leave of the <hi>Pope.</hi> Under pretence whereof, the <hi>Clergy</hi> at this Parliament at St. <hi>Edmunsbury,</hi> refuſed to be contributory to the Kings occaſions, when the <hi>Lay-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the Houſe had been forwards in it. The King being herewith much offended, gives them a further day to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider on it, Adjourning the Parliament to <hi>London,</hi> there to begin on the morrow after St. <hi>Hilaries</hi> day; and in the mean time commanded all their Barnes to be faſt ſealed up. The day being come, &amp; the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſtill perſiſting in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer obſtinacy, <hi>Excluſo &amp; Parliamento Clero Conſilium Rex cum ſolis</hi> Baronibus <hi>&amp; populo habuit, totumque ſtatim</hi> Clerum <hi>protectione ſua privavit</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqu. Brit. in R. Winchelſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note> the King (ſaith the Hiſtorian) excluding the <hi>Clergy</hi> out of the Parliament, adviſed with his <hi>Barons,</hi> and his people only, what was beſt to be done, by whoſe advice he put the <hi>Clergie</hi> out of his protection, and thereby forced them to conform to his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>ſumma totalis</hi> of the buſineſſe, and comes unto no more but this, that a particular courſe was adviſed in Parliament on a particular diſpleaſure taken by the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the body of his <hi>Clergy</hi> then convened together, for their particular refuſal to contribute to his wants and Wars, the better to reduce them to their natural duty. Which makes not any thing at all againſt the right of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> or for excluding them that Houſe, or for the validity of ſuch <hi>Acts</hi> as are made in Parliament during the time of ſuch excluſion; eſpecially conſidering that the King ſhortly after called his <hi>States</hi> together, and did excuſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53271:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelf for many extravagant Act which he had committed<note n="(†)" place="margin">Wolſingh. in Edw. the <hi>1.</hi> Anno <hi>1297.</hi>
               </note> againſt the Liberties of the Subject (whereof this was one) laying the blame thereof on his great occaſions, and the neceſſity which the Warrs which he had abroad did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon him.</p>
            <p>And ſo much as in anſwer unto that Record, ſuppoſing that the words thereof be rightly ſenced, as I think they are not, and that by <hi>Clerus</hi> there we are to underſtand <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as I think we be not, there being no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord (I dare boldly ſay it) either of Hiſtory or Law, in which the word <hi>Clerus</hi> ſerves to ſignifie the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> excluſive of the other <hi>Clergy;</hi> or any writing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, wherein it doth not either ſignifie the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> generally, or the <hi>inferiour Clergy</hi> only excluſive of the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops Biſhops,</hi> and other Prelates. Therefore in anſwer unto that ſo much applauded Cavill of <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> from what Record ſoever it either hath been hitherto, or ſhall hereafter be produced, I ſhall propoſe it to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſober Reader, whether by <hi>Clerus</hi> in that place or in any other of that kind and time, we muſt not underſtand the <hi>Inferiour Clergy,</hi> as they ſtand diſtinguiſhed in the Laws from my Lords the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>For howſoever it be true that <hi>Clerus</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> notion of the word doth ſignifie the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> generally, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons: Yet in the Legal notion of it, it ſtands diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and ſignifyeth only the inferiour <hi>Clergy.</hi> Thus do we find the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> of this Realm divided into <hi>Prelates, men of Religion,</hi> and other <hi>Clerks,</hi> 3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. the <hi>Seculars</hi> either into <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Clerks,</hi> 9 <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. or <hi>Prelates,</hi> and <hi>Clerks beneficed,</hi> 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. or generally into the <hi>Prelates</hi> and the <hi>Clergy,</hi> 9 <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. 14 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and 3. 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.2.7. and 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.2.4. and 8 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. And in all Acts and grants of Subſidies made by the <hi>Clergie</hi> to the Kings or Queens of <hi>England</hi> ſince the 32 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. (when the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie Subſidies firſt began to be confirmed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>So alſo in the <hi>Latin</hi> Idiom, which comes neereſt home,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53271:10"/>
               <hi>Nos Prelati &amp; Clerus,</hi> in the ſubmiſſion of the <hi>Clergy</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth,<note n="(†)" place="margin">Regiſt. Watham.</note> and in the ſentence of divorſe againſt <hi>Anne of Clere,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Regiſt. Cranmer.</note> and in the Inſtrument of the grant of the <hi>Clergy</hi> Subſidies preſented to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the <hi>27th.</hi> of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and in the form of the Certificates (<hi>per</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Stat. <hi>8.</hi> Eliz. c. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; ever fince</note> 
               <hi>Praelatos &amp; Clerum</hi>) returned by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to the Lord <hi>High Treaſurer,</hi> and finally, <hi>Nos Epiſcopi,</hi> &amp; Clerus Cantuatienſis Provinciae <hi>in hac Synodo more noſtro ſolito, dum Regni Parliamentum</hi> celebratur, Congregati.<note n="(†)" place="margin">Stat. <hi>1.</hi> Phil. &amp; Mary c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> in the Petition to <hi>K: K. Phillip</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> about the confirmation of the Abby Lands to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees; So that though many Statutes have been made in theſe latter times, <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> the Clergy, that is to ſay, the inferiour <hi>Clergy</hi> (who antiently had their place in Parliaments) being quite ſhut out, and utterly excluded from thoſe publique Councils; Yet this proves nothing to the point, that any <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> hath been counted good, to which the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were not called, or at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of which <hi>Act,</hi> they either were <hi>ſhut out</hi> by Force, or excluded by Cunning.</p>
            <p>But then beſides the ſo much celebrated Argument of <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> the Author of the Pamphlet before remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, hath told us ſomewhat on the credit of <hi>Kilbancies</hi> book; In which the Juſtices are made to ſay 7 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <q>That our <hi>Soveraign Lord the King,</hi> may well hold his <hi>Parliament</hi> by him, and his <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords, and by the <hi>Commons</hi> alſo, without the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Lords, for that the <hi>Spiritual Lords,</hi> have not any place in the <hi>Parliament</hi> Chamber, by reaſon of their <hi>Spiritualties,</hi> but by reaſon of their <hi>Temporal</hi> poſſeſſions.</q> But firſt, this is but the opinion of a private man, of no Authority or Eſteem (for ought we can find) in the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore not concluding in ſo great a buſineſſe. And <hi>2ly.</hi> admitting him to be a man of more note and credit than perhaps he was, yet he muſt needs fall ſhort in all reſpects, both for <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi> of Chief Juſtice <hi>Coke,</hi> whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the contrary we have ſeen before. But <hi>3ly.</hi> it runs croſſe to the antient practice of the <hi>Saxon</hi> times, in which the Biſhops ſate in <hi>Parliament</hi> as <hi>Spiritual</hi> perſons, without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53271:11"/>relation, to their <hi>Temporal</hi> poſſeſſions, or their <hi>Barons Fees,</hi> as afterwards in the raign of the <hi>Norman</hi> Kings. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admitting that <hi>Kilbancies</hi> plea were of weight enough, to keep the Biſhops down from riſing to their place in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it muſt be ſtrong enough to exclude all the <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords; The <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords being called to Parliament on no other ground, than for the <hi>Temporal</hi> poſſeſſions which they hold by Barony. <hi>Adeo argumenta ab abſurdo petita, ineptos habent exitus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Lactantius</hi> truly, It is the Fate (ſaid he) of ill choſen <hi>Premiſes,</hi> that they produce ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and abſurd <hi>Concluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remains one Objection more, and indeed the greateſt, not extant in the Pamphlet before remembred, though poſſibly promoted and occaſioned by it; that is to ſay, that the Biſhops are excluded from their Place and Vote by Act of Parliament, deliberately made and paſſed by the Kings conſent. For anſwer whereunto, it will be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary firſt to ſtate this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether that any two of the <hi>three Eſtates:</hi> confirming or agreeing together, may conclude any thing which tends to the Subverſion of the third. <hi>Bodinus</hi> that renowned <hi>Stateſman,</hi> hath reſolved it negatively, and determined thus; <hi>Nihil a duobus ordinibus diſcerni poſſe, quo uni ex tribus incommodum inferatur,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="(†)" place="margin">Bodin de Rep. l. <hi>3.</hi> s. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> That nothing can be done by two of the <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> to the diſprofit of the third, in caſe the point propoſed be ſuch as concerns them ſeverally, And he reſolved thus in favour of the <hi>Commons</hi> of the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> who were upon the point of being excluded from the Parliament, or Convention of the <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> if he had not notably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirred himſelf in their behalf (he being then a <hi>Delegate</hi> or Commiſſioner for one of the Provinces) and by his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and care preſerved their Intereſts; And to preſerve their Intereſt, he inſiſted chiefly on the antient cuſtomes of the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> as alſo of the Realms of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> In each of which it was received for a ruled Caſe, <hi>Nihil a duobus ordinibus ſtatui poſſe, quo uni ex tribus prejudicium crearetur,</hi> That nothing could be done by any of the <hi>two Eſtates,</hi> unto the prejudice of the third.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53271:11"/>
            <p>And if it were a ruled Caſe, then in the Engliſh Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, there is no reaſon why it ſhould be otherwiſe in the preſent times, the Equity and Juſtice of it being ſtill the ſame, and the ſame reaſons for it now as forcible as they could be then. Had it been otherwiſe reſolved of in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, wherein the <hi>Clergy</hi> were ſo prevalent in all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Counſels, how eaſie a matter had it been for them, either by joyning with all the <hi>Nobility</hi> to exclude the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> or by joyning with the <hi>Comonalty</hi> to exclude the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles?</hi> Or having too much Conſcience to venture in ſo great a change, and alteration, ſo Incompatible, Inconſiſtent with the Conſtitution of a Parliament; how eaſily might they have ſuppreſſed the <hi>Potency,</hi> and impair the <hi>Priveleges</hi> of either of the other two, by working on the humours or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the one to keep down the other?</p>
            <p>Nor doth it help the matter in the leaſt degree to ſay that the Excluſion of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> from the Houſe of Peers, was not done meerly by the procurement of ſome of the other two Eſtates, but by the Aſſent of the King, of whom the Laws ſay <hi>He can do no wrong,</hi> And by an Act of Parliament whereof our Lawyers ſay, <hi>que nul doit imaginer choſe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">Plowden in Commentar.</note> that no man is to think diſhonourable. For we know well in what condition the King was when he paſſed that <hi>Act,</hi> to what extremities he was reduced, on what terms he ſtood, how he was forced to withdraw from his City of <hi>London,</hi> to part with his dear Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and in a word, ſo over-powred by the prevailing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the two Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that it was not ſafe for him (as his Caſe then was) to deny them any thing. And for the Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> thus inſiſted on, beſides that the Bill had been rejected when it was firſt brought unto the <hi>Lords,</hi> and that the greater part of the <hi>Lords</hi> were frighted out of the Houſe, when contrary unto the courſe of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it was brought again; it is a point reſolved both in Law and Reaſon, that the Parliament can do nothing to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it ſelf, and that ſuch Acts as are under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, are not good and valid, whereof we have a fair ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the book of Statutes.<note n="(†)" place="margin">15 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53271:12"/>
            <p>
               <q>For whereas the King had granted certain Articles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be granted in the Form of a Statute, expreſly contrary to the Laws of the Realm, and his own Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Rights Royal <hi>(mark it for this is juſt the caſe)</hi> which he had yielded to eſcue the dangers, which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of the ſame were like to follow in the ſame Parliament,</q> it was <hi>repealed</hi> in theſe following words; <hi>It ſeemed good to the ſaid Earls, Barons, and other wiſe men, that ſince the Statute did not proceed of our free</hi> Will, the ſame be void; and ought not to <hi>have the name nor ſtrength of a</hi> Statute, <hi>and therefore by their Counſell and Aſſent we have decreed the ſaid</hi> Statute <hi>to be void, &amp;c.</hi> Or if it ſhould not be repealed in a Formal manner, yet is this Act however gotten, void in effect already by a former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, in which it was enacted in full Parliament, and at the ſelf ſame place where this Act was gained, <hi>That the Great Charter</hi> (by which, and many other Titles, the Biſhops held their place in Parliament) <hi>ſhould be kept in all points, and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Statute <hi>be made to the contrary, it ſhall be holden for none.</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>More Arguments than theſe againſt the Biſhops Place and Vote in Parliament I have no where found. And theſe being anſwered and refelled, I hope the point in queſtion hath been fairly proved, <hi>viz. That the Biſhops make a Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental and Eſſential part of our Engliſh Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53271:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
